Tristan RH Goodbody Ph.D.

REMOTE SENSING OF FORESTS RESEARCHER

University of British Columbia, Vancouver

□+604 992 1327 | ☑ goodbody.t@gmail.com | ☑ 0000-0002-6894-7925 | ☑ tgoodbody | У Goodbody |

About me

8 years experience and doctorate in remote sensing, machine learning and data fusion in the context of forest inventory and resources management. Collaborating with multiple levels in government, private industry and academia. Producing high impact science that continues to be operationalized. Mentoring students of all levels of post-secondary education in remote sensing, data science and forest management.

Research Interests

Forest Management Forest attribute mapping, forest mensuration & sampling

Remote sensing Airborne lidar & digital photogrammetric point clouds, drone-based datasets, sattellite imagery

Data science Predictive modelling, spatial data, reproducible science

Enhanced forest inventory Integrating remotely sensed data into forest management and planning frameworks

Ecosystem processes and function Vegetation structure, flora and fauna, disturbances & climate change

Experience

Post-Doctoral Fellow Vancouver, BC

FACULTY OF FOREST RESOURCES MANAGEMENT (UBC)

June 2019 - Present

- · Assessment of wood attributes using remote sensing (AWARE) & Canadian Wood Fibre Center Forest Innovation Program.
 - Initialized and maintained a two year international committee (academic, government, industry) to develop the opensource sgsR package, which has been widely adopted
 - Maintaining the sgsR package on CRAN and GitHub
 - Consulting with private industry and government to process and analyze lidar and digital photogrammetric data
 - Developing lidar processing and analysis frameworks to enhance forest inventory knowledge
 - Collaborating with Canadian federal government to generate digital photogrammetric benchmarks for landscape level inventories
 - Modelled potential human-wildife interactions and culturally important plant species using species distribution models
 - Publishing in high impact journals with high rate of citations
 - Mentoring graduate students in remote sensing dataset acquisition, processing, analytics, scientific communication, & writing
 - Contributed to indepth literature reviews of remote sensing forest inventory practices and future directions

Teaching assistant Vancouver, BC

FACULTY OF FOREST RESOURCES MANAGEMENT (UBC)

May 2015 - March 2019

- Lead & supervised applied exercises to guide student knowledge of remote sensing concepts.
 - FRST 443 Remote sensing for ecosystem management; FRST 521 Advanced earth observation and image processing
 - Guided students to success in written and oral submissions
 - Guest lectured on advanced remote sensing systems and data processing techniques
 - Developed graduate labs and evaluated research proposals & assignments

Planning Forester Intern - Co-op

Chetwynd, BC

CHETWYND FOREST INDUSTRIES - WEST FRASER MILLS LTD.

May 2014 - December 2014

- Worked in a team and individually to implement West Fraser Management objectives.
 - Site plan preparation
 - Harvest planning & layout
 - Silviculture assessments and reforestation quality inspections
 - Post-fire salvage planning and management
 - Forest appraisals

Planning Forester Intern - Co-op

Williams Lake, BC

May 2013 - September 2013

ALEX FRASER RESEARCH FOREST (UBC)

- Implemented planning and management perscriptions.
 - Road & timber layout
 - Timber cruising
 - Volume determination
 - Avian habitat assessments

Education

University of British Columbia

Vancouver, BC

Ph.D. Remote Sensing of Forests

May 2015 - March 2019

· Assessing the role of digital aerial photogrammetry for characterizing forest structure and enhancing forest inventories

University of British Columbia

Vancouver, BC

BSc Natural Resources Conservation (Hons.& Co-op)

September 2010 - January 2015

- · Science and Management Major.
 - Cons 330: Conservation Policy
 - FRST 443: Remote Sensing Of Ecosystem Management

Applied Skills

Remote Sensing Forest attribute modelling, point cloud processing, digital aerial photogrammetry, drone data sets

Data Science R (Advanced), machine learning, image processing, ecological modelling, inventory analysis, software development

Collaboration International academic, government, and industry representatives

Writing Scientific publications, public reports, funding grants, reproducible reporting **Communication** Confident public speaker, graduate student mentor, effective graphic design

Soft Skills

Personal Accountable, adaptable, assertive, confident, dependable, diligent, enthusiastic, friendly, reliable, respectful, positive

Social Conflict resolution, emotionally & culturally intelligent, equitable, leadership, inclusive, negotiation, team-building

Methodological Analytical, proactive, problem-solving, organized, time management, work ethic

Languages English/Spanish, German (basic)

Awards

Ph.D. FundingVancouver, BC

NSERC PGSD (\$63,000) 2018

Ph.D. FundingVancouver, BC

HARRY G. SMITH SCHOLARSHIP (\$4,600)

Peer-Reviewed Publications

Google Scholar Total citations: 1135 , h-index: 17 **Web of Science** Total citations: 745 , h-index: 13

- 1. Achim, A., Moreau, G., Coops, N. C., Axelson, J. N., Barrette, J., Bédard, S., Byrne, K. E., Caspersen, J., Dick, A. R., D'Orangeville, L., et al. (2022). The changing culture of silviculture. *Forestry*, 95(2), 143–152.
- 2. Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Goodbody, T. R., Achim, A., & Mulverhill, C. (2022). Framework for near real-time forest inventory using multi source remote sensing data. *Forestry: An International Journal of Forest Research*.
- 3. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Srivastava, V., Parsons, B., Kearney, S. P., Rickbeil, G. J., & Stenhouse, G. B. (2021). Mapping recreation and tourism use across grizzly bear recovery areas using social network data and maximum entropy modelling. *Ecological Modelling*, 440, 109377.
- 4. Toit, F. du, Coops, N. C., Goodbody, T. R., Stoehr, M., & El-Kassaby, Y. A. (2021). Deriving internal crown geometric features of douglas-fir from airborne laser scanning in a realized-gain trial. *Forestry: An International Journal of Forest Research*, 94(3), 442–454.
- 5. Fu, X., Zhang, Z., Cao, L., Coops, N. C., Goodbody, T. R., Liu, H., Shen, X., & Wu, X. (2021). Assessment of approaches for monitoring forest structure dynamics using bi-temporal digital aerial photogrammetry point clouds. *Remote Sensing of Environment*, 255, 112300.
- 6. Tompalski, P., Coops, N. C., White, J. C., Goodbody, T. R., Hennigar, C. R., Wulder, M. A., Socha, J., & Woods, M. E. (2021). Estimating changes in forest attributes and enhancing growth projections: A review of existing approaches and future directions using airborne 3D point cloud data (feb, 10.1007/s40725-021-00135-w, 2021). *Current Forestry Reports*, 7(1), 25–30.
- 7. Tompalski, P., Coops, N. C., White, J. C., Goodbody, T. R., Hennigar, C. R., Wulder, M. A., Socha, J., & Woods, M. E. (2021). Publisher correction: Estimating changes in forest attributes and enhancing growth projections: A review of existing approaches and future directions using airborne 3D point cloud data. *Current Forestry Reports*, 7(1), 25–30.

- 8. Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Goodbody, T. R., Queinnec, M., Luther, J. E., Bolton, D. K., White, J. C., Wulder, M. A., Lier, O. R. van, & Hermosilla, T. (2021). Modelling lidar-derived estimates of forest attributes over space and time: A review of approaches and future trends. *Remote Sensing of Environment*, 260, 112477.
- 9. Kearney, S. P., Larsen, T. A., Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., & Stenhouse, G. B. (2021). Characterizing off-highway road use with remote-sensing, social media and crowd-sourced data: An application to grizzly bear (ursus arctos) habitat. *Remote Sensing*, 13(13), 2547.
- 10. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Luther, J. E., Tompalski, P., Mulverhill, C., Frizzle, C., Fournier, R., Furze, S., & Herniman, S. (2021). Airborne laser scanning for quantifying criteria and indicators of sustainable forest management in canada. *Canadian Journal of Forest Research*, 51(7), 972–985.
- 11. Coops, N. C., Achim, A., Arp, P., Bater, C. W., Caspersen, J. P., Cote, J.-F., Dech, J. P., Dick, A. R., Ewijk, K. van, Fournier, R., et al. (2021). Advances in the application of remote sensing for forest information needs in canada: Lessons learned from a national collaboration of academic, industry, and government stakeholders. *Forestry Chronicle*, 97(2), 127–147.
- 12. Goodbody, T. R., White, J. C., Coops, N. C., & LeBoeuf, A. (2021). Benchmarking acquisition parameters for digital aerial photogrammetric data for forest inventory applications: Impacts of image overlap and resolution. *Remote Sensing of Environment*, 265, 112677.
- 13. Czekajlo, A., Coops, N. C., & Goodbody, T. R. (2021). Untangling the effect of urban vegetation type and structure on spectrally unmixed greenness. *Remote Sensing Letters*, *12*(12), 1216–1226.
- 14. Coops, N. C., Achim, A., Arp, P., Bater, C. W., Caspersen, J. P., Côté, J.-F., Dech, J. P., Dick, A. R., Ewijk, K. van, Fournier, R., et al. (2021). Advancing the application of remote sensing for forest information needs in canada: Lessons learned from a national collaboration of university, industrial and government stakeholders. *The Forestry Chronicle*, 97(2), 109–126.
- Toit, F. du, Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Goodbody, T. R., El-Kassaby, Y. A., Stoehr, M., Turner, D., & Lucieer, A. (2020). Characterizing variations in growth characteristics between douglas-fir with different genetic gain levels using airborne laser scanning. *Trees*, *34*(3), 649–664.
- 16. Goodbody, T. R., Tompalski, P., Coops, N. C., White, J. C., Wulder, M. A., & Sanelli, M. (2020). Uncovering spatial and ecological variability in gap size frequency distributions in the canadian boreal forest. *Scientific Reports*, 10(1), 1–12.
- 17. Xu, Z., Shen, X., Cao, L., Coops, N. C., Goodbody, T. R., Zhong, T., Zhao, W., Sun, Q., Ba, S., Zhang, Z., et al. (2020). Tree species classification using UAS-based digital aerial photogrammetry point clouds and multispectral imageries in subtropical natural forests. *International Journal of Applied Earth Observation and Geoinformation*, *92*, 102173.
- 18. Goodbody, T. R., Tompalski, P., Coops, N. C., Hopkinson, C., Treitz, P., & Ewijk, K. van. (2020). Forest inventory and diversity attribute modelling using structural and intensity metrics from multi-spectral airborne laser scanning data. *Remote Sensing*, 12(13), 2109.
- 19. Roussel, J.-R., Auty, D., Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Goodbody, T. R., Meador, A. S., Bourdon, J.-F., De Boissieu, F., & Achim, A. (2020). lidR: An r package for analysis of airborne laser scanning (ALS) data. *Remote Sensing of Environment*, 251, 112061.
- 20. Chadwick, A. J., Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Hervieux, A., Bater, C. W., Martens, L. A., White, B., & Röeser, D. (2020). Automatic delineation and height measurement of regenerating conifer crowns under leaf-off conditions using UAV imagery. *Remote Sensing*, 12(24), 4104.
- 21. Gómez, C., Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Álvarez-Taboada, F., & Sanz-Ablanedo, E. (2020). Forest ecosystem monitoring using unmanned aerial systems. In *Unmanned aerial remote sensing* (pp. 173–196). CRC Press.
- 22. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., & White, J. C. (2019). Digital aerial photogrammetry for updating area-based forest inventories: A review of opportunities, challenges, and future directions. *Current Forestry Reports*, *5*(2), 55–75.
- 23. Goodbody, T. R. H. (2019). Assessing the role of digital aerial photogrammetry for characterizing forest structure and enhancing forest inventories [PhD thesis]. University of British Columbia.
- 24. Nuijten, R. J., Coops, N. C., Goodbody, T. R., & Pelletier, G. (2019). Examining the multi-seasonal consistency of individual tree segmentation on deciduous stands using digital aerial photogrammetry (DAP) and unmanned aerial systems (UAS). *Remote Sensing*, 11(7), 739.
- 25. Coops, N. C., Goodbody, T. R., & Cao, L. (2019). Four steps to extend drone use in research. Nature Publishing Group.
- 26. Yancho, J. M. M., Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Goodbody, T. R., & Plowright, A. (2019). Fine-scale spatial and spectral clustering of UAV-acquired digital aerial photogrammetric (DAP) point clouds for individual tree crown detection and segmentation. *Ieee Journal of Selected Topics in Applied Earth Observations and Remote Sensing*, 12(10), 4131–4148.
- 27. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Hermosilla, T., Tompalski, P., & Crawford, P. (2018). Assessing the status of forest regeneration using digital aerial photogrammetry and unmanned aerial systems. *International Journal of Remote Sensing*, 39(15-16), 5246–5264.
- 28. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Hermosilla, T., Tompalski, P., McCartney, G., & MacLean, D. A. (2018). Digital aerial photogrammetry for assessing cumulative spruce budworm defoliation and enhancing forest inventories at a landscape-level. *Isprs Journal of Photogrammetry and Remote Sensing*, 142, 1–11.

- 29. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Hermosilla, T., Tompalski, P., & Pelletier, G. (2018). Vegetation phenology driving error variation in digital aerial photogrammetrically derived terrain models. *Remote Sensing*, 10(10), 1554.
- 30. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Crawford, P., & Day, K. J. (2017). Updating residual stem volume estimates using ALS-and UAV-acquired stereo-photogrammetric point clouds. *International Journal of Remote Sensing*, 38(8-10), 2938–2953.
- 31. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Marshall, P. L., Tompalski, P., & Crawford, P. (2017). Unmanned aerial systems for precision forest inventory purposes: A review and case study. *The Forestry Chronicle*, 93(1), 71–81.

Software & Guides_

- 1. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., & Queinnec, M. (2023). sgsR: Structurally guided sampling. https://tgoodbody.github.io/sgsR/
- 2. Roussel, J. R., Goodbody, T. R., & Tompalski, P. (2023). The lidR package. https://r-lidar.github.io/lidRbook/
- 3. Chadwick, A. J., Goodbody, T. R., Bater, C. W., Martens, L. A., Nuijten, R. J., Smith-Tripp, S., Grubinger, S., Irwin, L., Arkin, J., Hervieux, A., & Coops, N. C. (2022). Best practice guide to acquisition of 3D imagery from RPAS. https://irss-ubc.github.io/GDA_BPG_PUB/

Conferences_

Talaharia aha 11mina maidid 14 Milimaha m

ForestSAT Berlin, Germany SGSR: STRUCTURALLY GUIDED SAMPLING September 2022 Silvilaser Foz de Iguazu, Brazil October 2019 Uncovering spatial and ecological variability in gap size frequency distributions in the Canadian boreal forest **FRI Forest Practitioners Conference** Edmonton, AB ASSESSING THE STATUS OF FOREST REGENERATION USING DIGITAL AERIAL PHOTOGRAMMETRY AND UNMANNED AERIAL SYSTEMS October 2018 Silvilaser Blacksburg, USA November 2017 ASSESSING THE CAPACITY OF DAP TO ENHANCE INVENTORY KNOWLEDGE OF SPRUCE BUDWORM AFFECTED FORESTS Suquamish, USA Symposium on Systems and Analysis in Forest Resources UPDATING AIRBORNE LASER SCANNING EFI METRICS USING UAV ACQUIRED DAP POINT CLOUDS August 2017 **ForestSAT** Santiago, Chile MODELLING RESIDUAL STAND VOLUME USING UNMANNED AERIAL VEHICLES AND DIGITAL AERIAL PHOTOGRAMMETRY November 2016 **Canadian Remote Sensing Symposium** Winnepeg, MB MODELLING RESIDUAL STAND VOLUME USING UNMANNED AERIAL VEHICLES AND DIGITAL AERIAL PHOTOGRAMMETRY June 2016 **Southern Interior Silviculture Committee** Kamloops, BC DAP POINT CLOUDS ACQUIRED FROM UNMANNED AERIAL SYSTEMS (UAS) FOR ENHANCING FOREST INVENTORIES February 2016

Teaching & Instructional Workshop Experience ___

Technische Universität München	Freising, Germany
STRUCTURALLY GUIDED SAMPLING APPROACHES FOR FOREST INVENTORY	September 2022
Aalto University	Helsinki, Finland
STRUCTURALLY GUIDED SAMPLING APPROACHES FOR FOREST INVENTORY	September 2022
UBC - UTAS Workshop	Hobart, Australia
SGSR: A STRUCTURALLY GUIDED SAMPLING TOOLBOX FOR LIDAR-BASED FOREST INVENTORIES	April 2022
AWARE E-lecture Series	Online
DIGITAL PHOTOGRAMMETRIC APPLICATIONS TO ENHANCED FOREST INVENTORY	October 2019
CIF-IFC Workshop	Edmonton, AB
EXAMINING POTENTIAL APPLICATIONS OF UAS AND DIGITAL PHOTOGRAMMETRY FOR VARIOUS FOREST MANAGEMENT PURPOSES	April 2019
FRST 521 - Advanced earth observation and image processing	Vancouver, BC
GRADUATE COURSE - GUEST LECTURES ON LIDAR PROCESSING	May-Sept 2018
Nanjing University Workshop	Nanjing, China
DIGITAL PHOTOGRAMMETRY AND UAV FOR PRECISION FOREST INVENTORY	July 2018

LIDAR THEORY, PROCESSING AND IMPLEMENTATION WORKSHOP

AWARE Instructional Sessions

LIDAR THEORY, PROCESSING AND IMPLEMENTATION WORKSHOP

UAV and Remote Sensing Workshop

UAV and DIGITAL PHOTOGRAMMETRY FOR FORESTRY PURPOSES

Assessment of Wood Attributes for Remote Sensing AGM

Assessing The Capacity of DAP TO ENHANCE INVENTORY KNOWLEDGE OF SPRUCE BUDWORM AFFECTED FORESTS

February 2018

**Kapuskasing, Huntsville, ON

October 2017

October 2017

July 2017

**Assessment of Wood Attributes for Remote Sensing AGM*

**Assessing The Capacity of DAP TO ENHANCE INVENTORY KNOWLEDGE OF SPRUCE BUDWORM AFFECTED FORESTS

May 2017

Quesnel, Kamloops, BC

FP Innovations UAV WorkshopCourtney, BCUAVS AND THE UNIVERSITY OF BRITISH COLUMBIAOctober 2016

FRST 443 - Remote sensing for ecosystem management

Vancouver, BC

Undergraduate course - leading course labs

June 2015

Alex Fraser Research Forest Proof of Concept Workshop

Williams Lake, BC

RESEARCH IN USE OF DRONES TO UPDATE LIDAR FOREST INVENTORIES. LIDAR HIGH RESOLUTION INVENTORY FOR THE IDF

June 2015

International Journals

AWARE Instructional Sessions

Reviewer ISPRS Journal of Photogrammetry and Remote Sensing, Forest Ecosystems, Forestry Chronicle, Remote Sensing **Guest Editor** Remote Sensing Special Issue: Aerial and Near-Field Remote Sensing Developments in Forestry